hello and welcome back to the last part
of properties of inter molecular forces
specifically looking at molecular
compounds so things that are coent bound
so this one we're going to be just
looking at some demonstrations of how
hydron bonding can affect some of the
different properties of materials so how
does this all come about well if you
kind of think of in terms of particulate
Theory which was all about how different
particles interact with one another
we've used this description on all these
videos for a really long time of how we
can see that we have these particles
they're constantly moving um now one
thing about them is when they interact
with one another this takes a lot of
energy in order to separate them from
one another uh so they like to be
interacting each other so when we are
looking at something like this this is
known as a potential energy surface
which essentially the lower you are in
this little well here the lower the
energy is the more relaxed the molecules
are so one thing you can see is okay
when they two little orbs here they're
really close together this is like at
the very bottom this is as relaxed as
they can be they're really happy there
now the farther you pull them apart it's
going to take energy to pull them apart
so the farther you get away from this
line here the farther farther farther
you come away from each other the more
they're going to get pulled apart and it
takes energy to do that so what this
means is the stronger the inner
molecular force is the deeper this well
is meaning it's going to take a ton of
energy to separate say hydrogen bonding
versus dispersion dispersion is like you
can blow on it it'll fall off fall apart
so that's what we're going to look at
today
is is the strongest the intermolecular
forces the more Force so one thing to
kind of think about is
then more how can this have an effect on
big bulk properties of what you visually
can see is what we mean by bulk so when
you have like a cup of water or um you
know something that's sitting around
your house you can observe those things
so things with stronger intermolicular
forces usually have a higher boiling
point higher boiling point the other
thing that gets affected is if they
match we have the solubility or the
myability of how they mix together can
get affected too so matching forces like
dissolves like is a factor so let's take
a look at some of these things so we
learned about melting point and boiling
point what else can we have well the
first one is surface tension so what
that is all about is being if you have
let's say water molecules that are on a
in it within you take a little your a
little atom microscope and you look at
that level all of the water will
interact with each other making a
hydrogen bond Network and we've looked
at at similar things to like this in the
the past one would be if I were to let's
say uh play a video this video like this
one here and we were to look at it again
well on the left hand side you can see
that there is a network of all these
molecules they are hydrogen bonding to
each other on the right hand side is all
dispersion forces all interacting with
one another now the more this thing
heats up means it has more energy all
the little particles are kind of dancing
around more and more and more they're
moving at a really high rate as a result
it's going to start moving and breaking
and changing and it's going to affect
their properties so something that has a
really a really strong intermolecular
force can have a really high surface
tension meaning you can kind of walk on
water in a sense versus can you really
walk on air and it's not necessarily
possible Right without an airplane it
takes a lot of engineering Marvel to be
able to do that so the stronger that
framework is the more we're going to
actually see there let's take a look at
what this looks like in another
demonstration when it comes to surface
tension when we're trying to think of
this the ultimate Way is thinking of
like bugs and frogs on water right they
can walk on the water because of the the
webbing of their feet well another way
to see this is and on on the
International Space Station they're
always doing water demonstrations to
illustrate some of the different
properties here so water can do hydron
bonding meaning that it's being held
together with this intermolecular
framework
so what we're actually going to be
seeing is uh essentially Chris Johnson
who's one of the one of the astronauts
on the space station is going to collect
water with a paper towel he going to
kind of demonstrate how they can
actually like wash their face and things
like that but you can see like water he
can actually like shoot it out of the
water bottle and now the towel has
absorbed it all now what you're going to
see here is when he has to start to ring
it out is you'll see the layer of
hydrogen bonded water molecules all
around this thing so it's showing how
surface tension is holding together so
look at the little water layer that is
there and this something you can't do
easily on Earth but water can easily
hydrogen bond and hold itself together
right you can't see this with other
molecules at any normal given
temperature so water's able to hold
itself together like this you can see
how it spreads all over it hands it's on
the paper towel and it's because of the
gra the effects of gravity that they
make this possible but the surface
tension
of hydrogen bonding is what really
allows this to be possible which is
really like a really cool effect to see
hydrogen bonding is a fantastic thing to
be able to observe um where we can see
it firsthand via like from others from
from around the the planet or from space
right to show how we can see this the
other example is by imagining how let's
say insects can actually interact with
water right they can essentially walk on
water we can see that effect
it's really cool to see how that is now
you don't need to know the mathematics
behind this for my course but if you're
curious for physics then we can really
see that what other the forces are there
well there's also viscosity which is the
other one so how thick or goopy a
substances so when it came to surface
tension you can easily see that um easy
way to do is if you ever filled a glass
of water and you essentially filled it
to the point where you thought it was
going to overfill but it didn't so
you'll see that bubbled layer on the top
of the water
that is one way to imagine it viscosity
is the resistance for liquids to flow
meaning the stronger the forces the
harder it is for that to flow so one way
to kind of think of this is the bigger
the molecule the tougher it is so here I
have a bunch of viscosities for
different o for different levels of
carbon and we can see that the numbers
on the far right hand side are
increasing um going from one molecule to
the other so what exactly does this look
like in terms of of bigger molecules
higher dispersion when we can see this
change okay so in this video what we're
going to be looking at is I found a
video on YouTube that has viscosity
races essentially using different
ingredients found in food so here what
we have is from left to right is uh
maple syrup ketchup mustard and honey so
which are going to be used here and
pretty much something you could do at
home if you wanted to do it with really
young kids but essentially the viscosity
is how fast is it going to flow so syrup
as you know is a really sticky substance
it Tes it's actually usually really slow
especially when compared to water right
but if you think of these other
different ingredients which are a lot
heavier of a molecular composition and
have bigger molecules they flow very
very very slowly when they're on a plate
right so the stronger the intermolecular
force is the higher the dispersion is
the slower it's going to move the
thicker it is for the substance to
actually move one to the other so you
can kind of see like looking look at
these you know going from syrup to Honey
to ketchup and mustard barely moving at
all the higher the viscosity the slower
it's going to be so if you were trying
to figure out which of the molecules
here would have the highest viscosity
what could you exactly try to compare
well looking at all of them and this
same idea was with surface tension was
that you want to be able to compare what
forces they they have now with all these
all of them have dispersion they see CH4
C2 H6 C3 h8 they're all non-polar
same thing with cf4 C4 they're all
mainly tetrahedral they all have
non-polar bonds they are things that and
they all cancel out they're dipoles as
well so what can you exactly look at
well you're going to try to see which
one has the most electrons or the
highest molar mass is another way of
looking at it too so out of all these
right you can tell that going from a
through c c would be bigger than b and a
but what about with these other two
compounds down here they're a little
different well ccl4 is bigger than cf4
so you're pretty much comparing c and e
well looking at them chlorine has each
chlorine has 17 electrons that's almost
more than than most of than a lot of
this compound here right two chlorines
would be more than just almost one of
these so e is going to have the most
electrons which is the highest
polarizability out of all of them right
linking together dispersion all these
forces now the other different
properties we're going to look at too is
vapor pressure so what do we exactly
look at well this is how easy it is for
a chemical to become a gas without
boiling right so chemicals vaporize all
the time one way to think about this is
if you go outside in the early morning
you'll see that there's Dew on all the
grass and leaves and in your car in the
early morning but does it sit there all
day over time you see that that
evaporates you know so when it gets
really cold at night it condenses and
then over time it evaporates because it
gets enough heat or energy the water
isn't boiling off the grass it's
vaporizing so it's kind of it doesn't
have enough energy for it to to push
against the atmosphere and to leave and
become a vapor so it's all these little
gas molecules trying to escape so this
is something that constantly is
happening right you have the liquids
here you always have a little bit of gas
above the surface level which is also
possible you've seen it in my
demonstration with water molecules or
actually were little gas molecules
floating above before so it's it's the
push essentially are the liquids trying
to escape they they are being held back
by how strong those inter molecular
forces are but some of them are able to
break free uh when they're trying to get
out of there so when we're looking at
this something that's volatile means it
can easily evaporate nonvolatile does
not so what that means is the stronger
the inter molecular forces the lower the
vapor pressure meaning it's going to be
nonvolatile so something that doesn't
break so what is volatile well think of
when you go fill your car up one thing
that they tell you not to do is don't
smoke near the gas tanks which why is
that because gasoline is volatile
meaning that the gas that you can smell
is in the air so if you kind of light a
cigarette or something it's going to
potentially make the gas pump explode so
it's one of those things that you got to
kind of think about so the stronger they
are if it goes from let's say a solid
let's say a liquid to a gas it could
still be holding in place whereas if you
heat it up or give it enough energy
right through heat then it could
potentially break apart without even
reaching the boiling point so this is
volatile on the right and nonvolatile on
the left so this is something that's
like a dynamic process so this is one of
the reasons why we keep volatile liquid
liquids in sealed containers think of
your gas tank you got to close the cap
every time you do it if you didn't then
all your gas would be evaporate out of
your car by the end of the day if you
were not doing that because of this
state of dynamic equilibrium the liquid
that's at the bottom here is constantly
turning into a gas and it's going to
kind of Bounce all around its container
and then kind of make its way back into
the liquid and continue to cycle through
it's going from out then back in and it
constantly moves from one area to the
other so this is what we refer to as
dynamic equilibrium so to kind of like
wrap it up what we're trying to say here
with dynamic equilibrium is that
evaporation which is all about where you
have something that has a low
temperature molecule so here's all the
molecules they're all mainly lower
temperature they don't have a lot of
energy and that they're below what we
would consider is the escape point so
kind of like where it's boiling where it
has enough energy so one of the things
that make this easier well what can
accelerate it well is it all clumped
together or is it spread out over a big
surface so one way to think about this
is if you have like a glass of water and
let's say you spill the water all over
the counter so you and you put them both
next to each other which one will
evaporate first typically it's the
liquid that's spread over your whole
counter because it's being it's
interacting with more things that can
excite it to a higher temperature
so if these things get hotter then
what's going to happen is more molecules
are going to be able to escape that gas
phase and go into the you know into the
gases so it's not all of them will
become gases but over time you'll see
things will evaporate this what's
happening outside on your on your car
right in the early morning all that Dew
that's on your car and on the grass it's
in that lower temperature but as the day
gets hotter and hotter and hotter more
of it has enough energy that's been
absorbed absorbed from it from the from
the atmosphere from the Sun to be able
to heat up and to become a gas not
boiling but it's enough to evaporate now
to compare the two right boiling means
that essentially the liquid vapor
pressure matches air pressure because it
got so much energy where it's now able
to actually break through and join gas
phas okay so that's all I have for inter
molecular forces uh for for this set of
lectures I hope that this video These
videos helped you try to understand a
little bit more good luck trying to do
all your homework assignments out there
and thank you so much for listening and
please if you have not yet hit that like
subscribe button and I hope to see you
all in the future bye
now